Chuck Bradley, Ph.D.

Quantitative & qualitative researcher fluent in multiple research modalities

San Francisco, CA 94117 1 +1 215 630 2838 charles.roger.bradley@gmail.com c-huck.github.io/ inLinkedIn

Creative, detailed-focused professional with 10+ years of experience in quantitative research. PhD in Linguistics focusing on applying advanced statistics to uncover nuances of human behavior. Skilled in all stages of data analysis pipeline, from interviewing stakeholders on desired learnings, designing and fielding experiments, cleaning and transforming data, scripting statistical analyses, and weaving compelling data-backed narratives for business, academic, and general audiences. Demonstrated project management and interpersonal skills with 7+ years experience of leading small teams of researchers and other aspiring professionals. Conscientious, respectful of diversity, and eager to collaborate.

Key competencies

Storytelling | Project Management | Consumer research | User Experience (UX) | UX Research | Naming research | Experimental design | Survey programming (Qualtrics, MTurk, Optimal Workshop) | Data collection | In-depth interviews | Field methods | Custom Statistical Analysis / Statistical Programming (Python, Excel) | Database queries (Pandas/Python, SQL) | Data visualization and reporting | Machine learning (classification, prediction) | NLP | Critical thinking | Presentation Skills (business, academic, and general audiences) | Teamwork | Linguistics | Non-verbal communication / Sign language studies

Professional experience

Linguistic Researcher | Lexicon Branding | Sausalito, CA

Boutique brand naming and market research firm; Creators of Sonos, Blackberry, Swiffer and Pentium.

September 2021 to present

- I apply insights from structural and cognitive linguistics to create some of the most recognizable brand names at the world's leading naming agency. I lead a global network of 104 linguists, conduct qualitative and quantitative research, and contribute data-backed thought leadership on consumer behavior through effective brand names.
- 100+ projects as leader or integral team member across product naming, corporate rebranding, brand architecture, brand strategy, qualitative language and cultural evaluations, quantitative consumer research, localization, translation, and transliteration.
- Clients include: EY, AmerisourceBergen, Fannie Mae, Intuit/Quickbooks, Meta, Amazon, Intel, Visa, Procter & Gamble, PepsiCo, Philip Morris International, Expedia Group
- **Highlight:** *Meta, 2022*: Led team of three in design and execution of market research on wake words (like, 'Hey, Siri!'), polling 3,000+ participants across 5 international markets. Led team of two in design and execution of 19-country qualitative study interviewing international brand experts on cultural/linguistic challenges posed by each wake word. Synthesized both data streams into comprehensive report. Results indicated candidate wake words were not global-ready and provided details for additional refinement.
- **Highlight:** *Intuit Quickbooks, 2023*: Pitched and led quantitative brand architecture/customer experience study for QB's product portfolio using a modified tree-test + A/B test design. Results informed user navigation scheme for QB's SMB accounting portfolio. Responsible entire research trajectory, and for client education on research methodology.

Independent Researcher | Philadelphia, PA

May 2019 to Sept 2021

- I present new-to-the-world original research at international conferences, applying techniques from computer science to the study of human communication/interaction through embodied experience, like movement, manual action, and vision
- Prepared 1st author articles for publication with collaborators from top universities, leading experiment planning, fielding, analysis and visualization. See §Select Scholarly Output (pg. 2)
- Principal writer of three \$200k+ international grants in collaboration with University of Oslo and University of Edinburgh

Manager, Sign Language & Linguistics Lab | Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN

August 2013 to May 2018

- Trained and supervised teams of up to 10 student researchers per semester; 20+ students over entire appointment
- Worked closely with director in student recruitment, evaluation, retention
- Mentored student researchers one-on-one in developing research projects for end-of-semester department projects and Purdue student research fair; Most are now leading Speech Language Pathologists/professionals in their communities

Education

Ph.D. in Experimental Linguistics | Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN

August 2013 to May 2019

Dissertation: Transparency of transitivity in gesture, sign language

- Outcome: Demonstrated that syntactic and conceptual structure are visually linked in American Sign Language and gestures from non-signers, shedding light on a crucial stepping stone between gesture and (sign) language
- · Methods: structured elicitation, corpus analysis, and online perception studies via MTurk
- · Analyses: Machine-learning analysis (Naive Bayes & SVM), coded 100% in Python

M.A. in Experimental Linguistics | Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN

August 2010 to May 2013

Thesis: Motion events and event segmentation in American Sign Language

- Outcome: Demonstrated that the form of some ASL verbs can be predicted by how the world is physically shaped and how it is schematized. Drew critical comparisons between ASL verbs and map-drawing
- Methods: Semantic fieldwork/in-depth interviews in ASL
- · Analyses: Formal syntactic and semantic treatment

B.A., Independent Scholar (Linguistics), cum laude | Middlebury College, Middlebury, VT

September 2005 to June 2009

Thesis: A theoretical look at the person agreement marker in German Sign Language

- Outcome: Demonstrated that sign languages pose problems for linguistic theories created around spoken languages via the abnormal behavior of an agreement marker in German Sign Language. Suggested that rich visual imagery interacts tightly with more rigid linguistic system
- Methods/Analysis: Detailed literature review with original syntactic analysis

Technical skills, Languages

Natural languages: English (native), ASL (beginner) | Artificial languages: Python, SQL, MATLAB | Statistics/Methodology: Chi2, ANOVA, Linear and logistic regression, A/B testing, Tree-testing | Machine learning: Data preprocessing, Naïve Bayes, SVM/SVC, Bag-of-words, Clustering, PCA | Natural Language Processing: SpaCy, GLoVE, Word2Vec, NLTK | Versioning: Git / Github | Microsoft Office Suite: Word, Excel, Powerpoint, Outlook | Google Suite: Drive, Docs, Sheets (advanced formulas), Slides, Forms, Calendar | Other: fMRI (biomedical signal processing), Accessibility studies (deaf/hard-of-hearing)

Select scholarly output

- Bradley, C. and Wilbur, R. (2023), Visual Form and Event Semantics Predict Transitivity in Silent Gestures: Evidence for Compositionality. *Cognitive Science*, 47: e13331. (article) (project on GitHub)
- **Bradley, C.**, Malaia, E., Siskind, J. M. and R. B. Wilbur. (2022) Visual form of ASL verb signs predicts non-signer judgment of transitivity. PLOS ONE 17(2): e0262098. (article)
- Karabüklü, S., Wood, S. Sandra, **Bradley, C.**, Wilbur, R. B., and E. A. Malaia (*in prep.*). Sign language learning increases temporal resolution of visual attention. (manuscript)
- **Bradley, C.** (2022). Compositionality in 'Holistic' Pantomime Characterizes a Gesture-First Proto-Language. Talk presented at *Expression, Language, Music 1* (August 20–22, 2022)
- **Bradley, C.** (2021). Top-down and bottom-up sources of meaning in silent gesture. Talk presented at *AMLaP2021* (September 2–4, 2021) (abstract) (presentation)
- **Bradley, C.** (2021). Systematicity in gesture production, perception may support sign language emergence. Poster presented at the *CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing 34*. Philadelphia, PA, US. (abstract) (presentation)
- **Bradley, C.** (2019). Transparency of transitivity in pantomime, sign language. (Doctoral dissertation). Purdue University West Lafayette, IN. (dissertation)